There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we feature some
of the research
on the amount of influence
genetics on longevity.
And we start with a study
of thousands of twin pairs.
It has long been said that
the best hope for a long life
is to choose your parents
wisely.
After all, doesn't longevity
just run in the family?
Centenarians are people
who live to be at least 100,
and their siblings
are certainly more likely
to become centenarians
themselves,
and the parents of centenarians
have been found to be
more likely to have lived
to at least 90 years old.
On the other hand,
the lifespans of spouses
sometimes correlate as much,
or even more than,
those of genetic relatives.
Your partner may have as much
of an impact as your parent.
After all, genes aren't the only
things that get passed down.
Perhaps Grandma's
healthy recipes
or even a lifelong
love of running
runs in the family, too.
To tease out
the role of genetics,
researchers turn
to twin studies,
comparing difference between
identical twins
and fraternal twins.
For example, imagine
you're trying to determine
the role of genetics
in cancer--
the role played by genes,
versus other factors
that we may have control over.
Since identical twins share
100 percent of their genes,
whereas, on average, regular
twins only share 50 percent,
if genes play a large role,
then you'd expect that identical
twins would be more likely
to share the same fate
than fraternal twins, right?
If there were no difference
in the chances
that both sets of twins
got the same disease,
then it would appear
there's no genetic contribution.
It turns out that
the overwhelming contributor
to the causation of cancer
is not genetics,
but rather,
what we're exposed to.
Primary genetic factors
may only account
for 5 to 10 percent
of all cancers.
The BRCA genes popularized
by Angelina Jolie, for example,
may account for as little as
2 percent of breast cancers.
If one identical twin
gets breast cancer,
the likelihood the other
will too is only 13 percent,
despite having
essentially identical DNA.
Now, that's higher
than shared rates
among nonidentical twin women,
so there is a genetic component,
but genes only appear
to make a minor contribution
to cancer risk.
This is consistent with
the rates of common cancers
profoundly differing by as much
as 200-fold around the world.
What do twin studies have to say
about the heritability
of lifespan?
Based on a study
of thousands of twin pairs,
the heritability of longevity
was 26 percent for men
and 23 percent for women.
Subsequent twin studies have
arrived at a similar estimate:
approximately 25 percent
of our lifespan is determined
by our genetic differences,
which means
how we live our lives
may determine
the bulk of our destiny.
Estimates using other methods
tend to fall in
the 15 to 30 percent range.
For example, an analysis
of millions of family trees
from 86 million public profiles
in an online genealogy database
led to an estimate
of 16 percent,
though due to so-called
"assortative mating,"
meaning the fact that
we tend to pair up with mates
similar to ourselves,
rather than at random,
that may actually be
an overestimate.
Chosen partners often have
similar lifestyles,
so some of that
16 percent estimate
may have been influenced
by families sharing
similar diets
and healthy habits,
and not exclusively their genes.
Taking that into account,
the actual heritability
of lifespan may even be
well below 10 percent.
To leverage
the lifespan leeway we have
beyond the relatively small
genetic component,
we must first understand
the aging pathways
that account for
the nine hallmarks of aging.
The term "anti-aging" has been
much abused in popular culture,
attached to all manner
of unproven products
and procedures.
The term should probably
be reserved for things
that can delay or reverse aging
through the targeting
of one or more of the
established aging mechanisms.
In a landmark paper
cited nearly 7,000 times
in the biomedical literature,
"The Hallmarks of Aging"
delineates nine
common denominators
of the aging process.
They are Genomic Instability,
the accumulation of DNA damage.
Telomere Attrition,
the loss of the protective caps
at the end of our DNA strands.
Epigenetic Alterations,
changes in the way
our genes are expressed.
Loss of Proteostasis,
the buildup
of misfolded proteins.
Deregulated Nutrient Sensing,
metabolic alterations
particularly sensitive to diet.
Mitochondrial Dysfunction,
the declining efficiency
of our cellular power plants,
Cellular Senescence,
the arrest of cell replication.
Stem Cell Exhaustion,
the loss of the potential
of our tissues to regenerate,
and Altered
Intercellular Communication,
the rise in
proinflammatory signals.
In our next story, we look at how
the so-called Alzheimer's gene APOE
is the single most important
gene for longevity
because of its role as a cholesterol
carrier throughout the body.
Though the genetic
contribution to lifespan
may be relatively minor,
are there specific genes
that have been associated
with longevity?
The leading method
for complex genetic mapping
is called genome-wide
association analysis,
which is essentially
a massive game of Go Fish,
comparing a million or more
letters of DNA
between groups
of similar people,
looking for a match.
So for example,
if you stretch out the DNA
of hundreds of centenarians
and compare those sequences
to that of noncentenarians,
is there a DNA letter
at a certain position
that centenarians share
disproportionately?
The problem is
hundreds of centenarians
are all researchers are
typically able to find.
Extremely long-lived
individuals,
such as centenarians,
comprise only a tiny fraction
of the population,
on the order of
1 in 10,000 or so.
As you can imagine,
the more people you have in
a genome-wide association study,
the more likely
you'll be able to find
a needle in the DNA haystack.
With so few people
available to study
for extreme longevity research,
it becomes much more difficult
to identify trends.
Some researchers have tried
solving this problem
by lowering the age requirement
to 85.
Then you can enroll
thousands into your study,
but making it to 90
is not the same
as making it to 100.
In fact, statistically, it's
as hard to get from 90 to 100
as it is to get to 90
in the first place.
So, by using
younger age brackets,
we may miss out on discovering
some secret centenarian sauce.
That brings us to the largest
genome-wide association study
of lifespan to date,
based on data
from a million people.
How were researchers able
to include so many subjects?
By correlating
the genetic fingerprints
of half a million
middle-aged individuals
with the ages
of both of their parents,
they were able to find
a dozen DNA regions
linked to lifespan
that appeared to account for
up to five years' difference
between individuals.
Twelve DNA markers is actually
a surprisingly low number,
compared to height,
for example,
which is determined by more than
400 different DNA spots--
although, unlike lifespan,
height is highly heritable.
A review of all
of the genome-wide
association studies
for longevity put together
only found one gene confirmed
in multiple independent
meta-analyses:
the "Alzheimer's gene,"
APOE.
Beyond just determining
lower or higher dementia risk,
APOE is the single
most important gene
when it comes to longevity--
though again, that's not
necessarily saying much.
APOE codes for a protein
that is 299 amino acids long
called apolipoprotein E.
Some people have APOE genes
that code for the protein
with the amino acid cysteine
at positions 112 and 158,
known as the APOE2 variant,
while others have
an arginine in those spots--
the APOE4 variant
of the protein,
and APOE3 is the third major
type of variant,
which has one of each.
Having genes that code
for the APOE4 variant
increases your risk
of cognitive decline,
full-blown Alzheimer's disease,
and premature death.
If you have one copy
of the APOE4 gene
from your mother or father,
your odds of becoming
a centenarian
are cut roughly in half,
and if you have APOE4 genes
from both parents,
your centenarian odds drop
by more than 80 percent.
What does this protein do
to have such a powerful impact
on our health and longevity?
APOE is the primary cholesterol
carrier in the brain
and plays a major role
packaging and transporting
LDL cholesterol
throughout the body.
The LDL cholesterol level
in those with APOE4 genes
averages more than
40 points higher
than those with APOE2 genes,
gunking up the arteries that
feed both the heart and brain.
LDL cholesterol is a risk factor
not just for heart disease
but Alzheimer's disease
as well.
Switch people to a diet
lower in animal fat
and cholesterol, though,
and those LDL differences
can disappear,
nearly a 60-point drop in LDL.
The difference
in cholesterol level
caused by
the different APOE genes
can simply disappear
if you eat a diet low enough in
saturated fat and cholesterol.
So diet can trump genetics.
This may explain
the so-called Nigerian paradox.
If you inherit one APOE4 gene,
your risk of getting Alzheimer's
may triple,
and if you get APOE4 genes
from both parents--
which occurs in about one
in fifty people in the US--
you might end up
with nine times the risk.
The highest frequency
of the APOE4 variant
occurs in Nigerians,
but they also have
some of the lowest rates
of Alzheimer's disease.
How can that be?
The population with the highest
rate of the "Alzheimer's gene"
has one of the lowest rates
of Alzheimer's disease?
This contradiction
may be explained
by Nigerians' extremely low
blood-cholesterol levels,
thanks to a diet
low in animal fat,
and consisting mainly
of grains and vegetables.
Humans may have evolved
to maintain an LDL level
of about 25,
but the average
in the Western world
is approximately 120.
It's no wonder heart disease
is the leading cause of death
in high-income countries,
and Alzheimer's disease,
according to
the World Health Organization,
is killer #2.
Too often, doctors and patients
have a fatalistic approach
to chronic
degenerative diseases,
and Alzheimer's is no exception.
"It's all in your genes,"
they say,
"and what will happen
will happen."
But research shows that although
you might have been dealt
some poor genetic cards,
you may be able
to reshuffle the deck with diet.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.